Teams are made up of individuals and
individuals are driven
by different motivators.
Whether that's serving their organization,
supporting their family or
simply working on projects
they think are cool.
You'll need to learn about
the people on your team,
in order to best determine how to
motivate everyone at the same time.
A few years ago,
researchers here at Google set out to
identify the dynamics of effective teams.
And through this research,
they identified five factors that
have an impact on team effectiveness.
In order of importance, those five
factors are: psychological safety,
dependability, structure and
clarity, meaning and impact.
Let's break these down.
Let's start with psychological safety,
which is the number one factor
that impacts team effectiveness.
Here's how our researchers define it.
Psychological safety refers to
an individual's perception,
of the consequences of taking
an Interpersonal risks.
In other words, they believe it's safe
to take risks within their team and
they don't risk being labeled as ignorant,
incompetent, negative or disruptive.
On teams with high psychological safety,
teammates feel comfortable taking
risks around fellow team members,
seeking differing opinions and resolving
interpersonal conflict when it comes up.
For example, on my team at Google,
we like to say be direct and kind.
We've worked really hard to build a team
culture, in which we can hold one another
accountable while maintaining a shared
space that is safe, secure, and peaceful.
What I found is that,
when opportunities to take risks do arise,
like pitching an out-of-the-box
idea to my directors, for example,
this culture of mutual respect, has
already laid the groundwork to get direct
feedback without frustration or
worrying that I might embarrass myself.
And that's been invaluable in maintaining
a high level of psychological safety for
the team.
Next, we have dependability.
Google's researchers explain it this way.
On dependable teams, members are reliable
and complete their work on time.
Creating a dependable team requires
the combination of setting,
negotiating and meeting expectations.
Yes, your team needs to meet
the expectations set for them.
At the same time,
you as a project manager need to establish
a two way relationship with your team.
You have to be able to clearly
communicate expectations and
ensure that the team feels comfortable
negotiating with you when needed.
For example, it's likely that
a person on your team works on two or
more projects with competing deadline.
If they're afraid to share
their own constraints with you,
then their work on both
projects might suffer.
Alternatively, if they come to you with
their concerns and open understanding and
negotiation around priorities
could help ease their burden.
Next, we have a structure and clarity.
Here's how our researchers define it.
Structure and clarity refers to
an individual's understanding of job
expectations, knowledge of how
to meet those expectations and
the consequences of their performance.
Each team member has a clear sense of
their individual role, plans and goals.
And they have a sense of how
their work affects the group.
You as the project manager,
can help foster a sense of structure and
clarity on the team.
For example, if a project structure in
tracking are sloppy, unorganized and
incohesive, then the team's output is
likely to be sloppy, unorganized and
incohesive.
This can cause tension within the team.
Alternatively, if you diligently engage
in project tracking, your team will have
clarity, feel more united and
will be able to effectively collaborate.
Meaning, also impacts team effectiveness.
Google's researchers defined
meaning in this context, as finding
a sense of purpose either in the work
itself or in the results of that work.
For example, your teammates might
find meaning in supporting themselves
financially, helping
the team reach its goals or
wanting their products to reach
a new community of users.
And finally, we have impact.
Our researchers define impact as
the belief that the results of
one's work matters and creates change.
It can be challenging for
people to notice how their work can
shift an entire ecosystem forward.
Part of your role as the project manager,
is to help individual teammates
identify how they drive impact both
within the team and beyond it.
Project tracking can be a helpful tool for
visualizing progress and impact.
Meeting milestones for example,
demonstrates to the team how their
individual tasks contribute
to the larger project goals.
For example, my team focuses
on routing within Google Maps.
The big idea is to focus on helping people
to get to where they're going on time.
So, everything we do should make that
experience incrementally better.
And that's how we add impact.
To recap, Google's researchers
identified psychological safety,
dependability, structure and
clarity, meaning and
impact as the top five factors that
have an impact on Team effectiveness.
Coming up,
we'll discuss how project managers
lead teams that reach project goals.